<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fiction.coach/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fiction.coach/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-07-18T15:56:12+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/</id><title type="html">Fiction Coach</title><subtitle>Write better stories. With solid case studies from great books, cult movies, beloved series and kick-ass games!</subtitle><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><entry><title type="html">How Rowling used Foreshadowing, Mystery, Pacing and Suspense</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/07/jk-rowling-foreshadowing-mystery-pacing-and-suspense" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Rowling used Foreshadowing, Mystery, Pacing and Suspense" /><published>2018-07-18T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-07-18T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/07/jk-rowling-foreshadowing-mystery-pacing-and-suspense</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/07/jk-rowling-foreshadowing-mystery-pacing-and-suspense">&lt;p&gt;Always – the pace is steady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always – the next step is foreshadowed by questions that arise in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And always – thanks to careful planning and grooming, Rowling knows what questions you’ll ask yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kind of like an author’s superpower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way Rowling wrote Harry Potter is nothing short of genius. That much we all know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the reason why Harry Potter became such a success is because &lt;strong&gt;the story of Harry Potter is a very good mystery story.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True, it’s also fantasy, but if you strip away the fantasy elements and look under the hood, you’ll find &lt;strong&gt;a story based on clues, deduction and a LOT of beautiful foreshadowing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JK Rowling wrote Harry Potter as a mystery story that always delivers and always stays true to its readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do I say that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because JK Rowling gives us the clues and doesn’t cheat our expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Francis Bacon said&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The job of the artist is always to deepen the mystery&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-athr&quot;&gt;Francis Bacon&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Harry Potter is a story that’s asking questions and makes you, the reader, find the answers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see why Harry Potter is such an addictive and rewarding book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we’ll cover:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-hook&quot;&gt;The Hook of Harry Potter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-mystery&quot;&gt;How JK Rowling used Mystery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;Foreshadowing in Harry potter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-pacing-and-suspense&quot;&gt;Pacing and Suspense in Harry Potter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;the-hook&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hook-of-harry-potter&quot;&gt;The Hook of Harry Potter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t talk about a successful mystery if you don’t want to find out more about it from the first two paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what better way to do that than through a great book opening, that hooks you right from the start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hook of Harry Potter and The Philosopher’s Stone consists of 4 paragraphs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can read the breakdown of this hook, right after the following quote:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mr. and Mrs. Dursley, of number four, Privet Drive, were proud to say that they were perfectly normal, thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They were the last people you'd expect to be involved in anything strange or mysterious, because they just didn't hold with such nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mr. Dursley was the director of a firm called Grunnings, which made drills. He was a big, beefy man with hardly any neck, although he did have a very large mustache. Mrs. Dursley was thin and blonde and had nearly twice the usual amount of neck, which came in very useful as she spent so much of her time craning over garden fences, spying on the neighbors. The Dursleys had a small son called Dudley and in their opinion there was no finer boy anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Dursleys had everything they ever wanted, but they also had a secret, and their greatest fear was that somebody would discover it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-athr&quot;&gt;Harry Potter and The Philosopher's Stone - JK Rowling&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see why this hook is so effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-might-be-the-most-famous-and-specific-hook&quot;&gt;This might be the most famous and specific hook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a dry and boring hook like “there was a dark and stormy night”, this 4 paragraph-long hook does multiple things well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We meet two important characters right off the bat &lt;strong&gt;– the Dursleys.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We find out their address &lt;strong&gt;– number four, Privet Drive –&lt;/strong&gt; and we think about them as real people. Because real people live in homes and homes have addresses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They’re “perfectly normal”. &lt;strong&gt;Who on Earth is “perfectly normal”?&lt;/strong&gt; We smell something – maybe a foreshadowing? – just around the corner, that’s the contrast to this &lt;strong&gt;“perfectly normal”&lt;/strong&gt; stuff. Maybe. Who knows?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humor and candor: &lt;strong&gt;“thank you very much”.&lt;/strong&gt; JK Rowling delights through her day-to-day humor, throughout all of the 7 books, which, again, makes us think about her characters as real people – a colossal feat, given that we’re interested in stories about people we empathize with. I’ll always be fascinated with &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/harry-potter-characters&quot;&gt;how JK Rowling created her Harry Potter characters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now, &lt;strong&gt;there really must be something fishy. We get one whole paragraph – the third – about how appallingly boring these people are&lt;/strong&gt; – how Mr. Dursley makes drills and how Mrs. Dursley cranes her neck spying on her neighbors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, the fourth paragraph &lt;strong&gt;– they also had a secret, and their greatest fear was that somebody would discover it –&lt;/strong&gt; grabs you by the ear and makes you turn the page, wanting to find the answer to “what can possibly be their secret?” Congrats! Mission accomplished!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that JK Rowling has us interested and got us to turn the page, she’s setting up the next phase: the inciting incident, when Harry gets his Hogwarts letter of admission. More on this in a moment, in the pacing and suspense part of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;the-mystery&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-jk-rowling-used-mystery&quot;&gt;How JK Rowling used Mystery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry Potter reminds us of the classic Sherlock Holmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been seduced by the secret superpower of deduction logic, a la Sherlock Holmes, then you now know why reading Harry Potter is such an adrenaline rush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Harry Potter books are a perfect balancing act of telling a mystery story without being obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;the-descriptions&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;recognizable-character-descriptions&quot;&gt;Recognizable character descriptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most compelling part of a story is a character. No author could ever create a compelling mystery, if they didn’t have great, recognizable characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the key ingredients of writing a successful mystery: create characters with signature physical traits and quirks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prove this, we have three characters from the Harry Potter universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you guess who these characters are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;black haired and severe-looking woman&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;half-moon spectacles with a long and crooked nose&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;greasy black hair and a hook nose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve guessed just one of these three, you’re living proof of how good JK Rowling’s skills are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the power of repetition, that JK Rowling uses so effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She’s spread those descriptions so cleverly, that every time you read&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“half-moon spectacles,” you know it’s Dumbledore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“severe-looking woman,” you know it’s Minerva McGonagall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“greasy black hair,” you know it’s all about Snape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;the-clues&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;clues&quot;&gt;Clues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any self-respected mystery, the Harry Potter books are peppered with clues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clues are crucial if you want to make your story believable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JK Rowling has a big advantage when it comes to clue placing in the fantasy of Harry Potter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The wonders of her magical elements hide the clues &lt;u&gt;just enough to help&lt;/u&gt; you anticipate the grand reveals, &lt;u&gt;but well enough to be lost&lt;/u&gt; among those distracting decorations of the magical and whimsical.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Placing clues at the right time and making them unnoticeable is an art that JK Rowling masters brilliantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see a few examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think about that time when Snape accused Harry of stealing polyjuice potion from his cabinet and a few days later Harry saw Barty Crouch on the Marauders' Map, inside Snape's cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Giving away that Alastor Moddy was in fact Barty Crouch Jr. in disguise.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or maybe the biggest clue in Book 1 is Harry's dream, at the end of his first day at Hogwarts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is one of many times Rowling pointed us to Quirrell's turban&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The talking turban from Harry's dream is clearly a clue for revealing Voldemort at the end of Book 1, sitting at the back of Quirrell's head.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or when Lupin steps in to protect Harry from the Dementor-Boggart and the boggart turns into a full moon.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full moon? Lupin?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't tell me professor Lupin is a werewolf!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of professor Lupin’s foreshadowing in Prizoner of Azkaban, of him being a lonely werewolf, this is another great thing that JK Rowling does: &lt;strong&gt;she creates complete and satisfying story arcs.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/the-theme-of-harry-potter&quot;&gt;overarching theme of the Harry Potter series&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Prizoner of Azkaban also has its own theme of lonelines and isolation,&lt;/strong&gt; which influences Harry’s point of view and his character development throughout the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Rowling does that brilliantly, &lt;strong&gt;by underlining Harry’s isolation from everyone else, through multiple techniques, the most obvious one being the use of Sirius Black and Remus Lupin: the lone wolf – Remus Lupin – and the cornered hound – Sirius Black,&lt;/strong&gt; symbols for Harry’s situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check out the &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/07/prizoner-of-azkaban&quot;&gt;breakdown of Prizoner of Azkaban&lt;/a&gt; for more of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;the-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;foreshadowing-in-harry-potter&quot;&gt;Foreshadowing in Harry potter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say that Harry Potter has an enormous amount of foreshadowing is an understatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The whole series is one big fat foreshadowing:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hagrid’s foreshadowing of Sirius Black, in the prologue of Book 1,&lt;/strong&gt; when he’s delivering baby Harry, with the help of “young Sirius Black’s” motorcycle. This is actually saying “young Sirius Black is a good guy, he wouldn’t rat out the Potters.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or that time, &lt;strong&gt;when Harry had a horrible feeling that Snape can read minds.&lt;/strong&gt; Guess what we find out Snape is accomplished in, four books later – Legilimency, the power to gaze inside a man’s mind.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And speaking of Legilimency, &lt;strong&gt;that’s how Voldemort knew that Harry lied about the Philosopher’s Stone in Book 1,&lt;/strong&gt; when the Mirror of Erised revealed the stone in Harry’s pocket, &lt;strong&gt;though we only learn that Voldermot is a Legilimens in Book 5.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And speaking of Voldemort, in Book 2, the first time &lt;strong&gt;Harry&lt;/strong&gt; sees Tom Riddle’s name, he &lt;strong&gt;has the strange feeling that he knows Tom.&lt;/strong&gt; Well, he should: he’s had a chunk of the guy’s soul stuck in him, since he was one year old.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or how Dumbledore gets “an odd look of triumph” after learning that Harry’s blood was used in Voldemort’s resurrection spell. It’s not until Book 7 that we get to find out that &lt;strong&gt;when Voldemort took Harry’s blood to restore himself, he tied Harry to his own life.&lt;/strong&gt; So while Voldemort still lived, Lily’s protection lived in Voldemort.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we essentially sipped every word that JK Rowling put on paper, with the intent of writing Harry Potter’s and Tom Riddle’s story – &lt;strong&gt;extraordinary amounts of top-notch quality foreshadowing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;the-pacing-and-suspense&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pacing-and-suspense-in-harry-potter&quot;&gt;Pacing and Suspense in Harry Potter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pacing is alternating the build-up with the rush.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like a slow and steady walk uphill, followed by a torrent of events, as you’re racing downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up and down, up and down, on and on, until your story reaches its end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The build-up is like a cooldown in reverse.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And then it’s followed by a meltdown – the reveal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build-up is when you make your readers turn the pages, with the help of elements like those we’ve covered earlier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-hook&quot;&gt;a great hook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;good foreshadowing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and tons of mysterious &lt;a href=&quot;#the-clues&quot;&gt;clues&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#the-descriptions&quot;&gt;descriptions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build-up allows your readers to enjoy the rush of the big reveals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more important thing to remember here is that you can’t have a perpetual build-up or a perpetual rush of events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you’ll either bore your readers to death or race their pulse into a heart attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;picture&gt;
	&lt;source media=&quot;(max-width: 991px)&quot; srcset=&quot;https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/mobile/pacing.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;nk-img-stretch&quot; src=&quot;https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/pacing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pacing.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/picture&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You need a balanced act: build-up / rush, build-up / rush.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how pacing helped JK Rowling sell her idea of a boy-wizard, when Harry gets his letter of admission from Hogwarts, but those nasty Dursleys won’t let him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-letters-from-no-one-meldtown&quot;&gt;“The Letters From No One” meldtown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the chapter where Harry gets his letter of admission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the third chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous two chapters, Rowling made sure we’ll empathize with Harry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know by now, the more you care about a character, the more eager you’ll be to turn the pages and find out the story contained within those pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a build-up of two chapters, where we find out how mean the Dursleys are to Harry, we see that he’s not even allowed to open his own mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this, we hungrily read on, hoping, just hoping that somehow…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Rowling is aware that this is the moment where she’ll win you or she’ll lose you for a reader. This is where you and the hero get the taste of what’s to come. This is what’s known as &lt;strong&gt;the inciting incident&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s why Rowling counts on your empathy for Harry: to keep on reading, because you want to find out how it will all go down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how she does that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The setup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry, an orphan boy, mistreated and resented by his adoptive family, finally has something out of the ordinary to stir him up: a personalized letter. And it’s all for himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The letter is so personal that its address is “to Mr. Harry Potter, The Cupboard Under the Stairs,” exactly where the Dursleys sent Harry to live. Who’d know these particular details? Reason to read more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, but it’s written in shiny green ink, with a wax seal on it. Who sends these out anymore? We read on to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we get to witness how weird the Dursleys react to this letter and we can’t stop asking “why are you so desperate in making Harry so miserable about this letter? Can’t you just let him read it? It’s his own property, after all!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Rowling begins the meltdown phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Uncle Vernon's face went from red to green faster than a set of traffic lights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it didn't stop there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Within seconds it was the grayish white of old porridge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-athr&quot;&gt;Harry Potter and The Philosopher's Stone - JK Rowling&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, but Harry gets to eavesdrop on the conversation between the Dursleys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not having one in the house, Petunia!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Didn't we swear when we took him in we'd stamp out that dangerous nonsense?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-athr&quot;&gt;Harry Potter and The Philosopher's Stone - JK Rowling&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this, Rowling has us hooked for the roller-coaster about to come, by simply showing us how the Dursleys reacted to this strange letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The build-up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how I named this &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the build-up?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;em&gt;the build-up of the meltdown.&lt;/em&gt; Because Rowling can’t outright show you what’s in that letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it would be a total buzzkill and the roller-coaster would come to a sudden stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why she’s created this build-up: to make you say to yourself the same thing you’ve been saying since page 1: &lt;strong&gt;“I wonder what’s gonna happen next.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s happening, now that the Dursleys have declared war on that letter? We follow Harry, as he’s trying to get that letter. Or as it turns out, the letter is trying to make its way to Harry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time the Dursleys prevent Harry from getting his letter, the scenes become longer and more dramatic and more dramatic and more dramatic, until they end up in an abandoned house, on a stranded rock of an island, in the middle of a storm. And the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The satisfying conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inciting incident, this whole race to prevent Harry from reading his letter, is brought to a delicious conclusion: a literal giant – Hagrid – slams down the door, terrifies the Dursleys, gives Dudley a pig tail and hands Harry his letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is how you end a meltdown, making your reader love your writing and giving you props for making it worth his time invested in the build-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-keeper-of-the-keys-and-diagon-alley-build-up&quot;&gt;“The Keeper of the Keys” and “Diagon Alley” build-up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve had a satisfying and fun race downhill and Harry got his letter, it’s time to slow down the pace and go into build-up mode again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Up and down, up and down, on and on, until your story reaches its end.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because you'll &lt;strong&gt;otherwise bore your readers to death or race their pulse into a heart attack.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these two chapters Rowling is doing three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;she’s introducing new characters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;she’s worldbuilding her universe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and &lt;strong&gt;while she’s worldbuilding, she’s making you ask questions that she’ll answer throughout the whole of the seven books.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now that he got his letter, is Harry going to fit in at Hogwarts?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who is Hagrid and why was he expelled from the wizarding school?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who is this Voldemort and what does he want with Harry?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it all sounds fun and games, but unlike an amateur, a pro author will always know &lt;strong&gt;how to pave the narrative with those questions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even more important than asking those questions is &lt;strong&gt;knowing how to answer those questions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how the next steps that Harry takes in his journey are always a result of his previous ones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harry as a mistreated adopted boy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harry getting his first letter and wanting to open it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;obstacles making us and Harry wonder what’s so special about that letter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new characters and settings that are making us wonder if Harry is going to be fit for Hogwarts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we got our answer to “what’s the letter all about?” we’ll ask ourselves “what’s Hogwarts like?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Rowling isn’t sending Harry anywere but there. Not back to the Dursleys. Because otherwise we’d lose focus and interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s how you create suspense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you’ve learned how Rowling uses mystery, suspense and foreshadowing, you’re well equipped to write hypnotic stories by yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one last thing I want you to remember, especially if you’re writing series:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everytime you're pursuing one big question with your story structure -- scene after scene --, keep the readers interested by placing secondary questions in their mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This will make sure they'll stick around.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end this with an example, look at the progression of these questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what’s in the letter?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what’s it gonna be like at Hogwarts?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why did Hagrid get expelled from Hogwarts?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And remember that last question next time you read Book 2 of Harry Potter :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="featured" /><category term="On Writing" /><category term="Book Studies" /><category term="Movies" /><category term="JK Rowling" /><category term="Harry Potter" /><category term="Foreshadowing" /><summary type="html">The way Rowling wrote Harry Potter is nothing short of genius. That much we all know.But the reason why Harry Potter became such a success is because the story of Harry Potter is a very good mystery story.Let's see why Harry Potter is such an addictive and rewarding book.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/jk-rowling.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Prizoner Of Azkaban</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/07/prizoner-of-azkaban" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prizoner Of Azkaban" /><published>2018-07-16T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-07-16T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/07/prizoner-of-azkaban</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/07/prizoner-of-azkaban"></content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Rowling used series as threads for Order of The Phoenix plot</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/07/jk-rowling-series-order-phoenix" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Rowling used series as threads for Order of The Phoenix plot" /><published>2018-07-02T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-07-02T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/07/jk-rowling-series-order-phoenix</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/07/jk-rowling-series-order-phoenix"></content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="On Writing" /><category term="Book Studies" /><category term="Movies" /><category term="JK Rowling" /><category term="Harry Potter" /><category term="Structure" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/jk-rowling.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Create Characters like JK Rowling</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/harry-potter-characters" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Create Characters like JK Rowling" /><published>2018-06-25T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-06-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/06/harry-potter-characters</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/harry-potter-characters"></content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="On Writing" /><category term="Book Studies" /><category term="Movies" /><category term="JK Rowling" /><category term="Harry Potter" /><category term="Character" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/jk-rowling.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Arya will kill The Mountain - a Foreshadowing Study</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-arya-kills-the-mountain-foreshadowing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Arya will kill The Mountain - a Foreshadowing Study" /><published>2018-06-20T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-06-20T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-arya-kills-the-mountain-foreshadowing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-arya-kills-the-mountain-foreshadowing"></content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="On Writing" /><category term="Book Studies" /><category term="Series" /><category term="GoT" /><category term="Game of Thrones" /><category term="Foreshadowing" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/arya-mountain.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Theme of Harry Potter</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/the-theme-of-harry-potter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Theme of Harry Potter" /><published>2018-06-18T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-06-18T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/06/the-theme-of-harry-potter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/the-theme-of-harry-potter"></content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="On Writing" /><category term="Book Studies" /><category term="Movies" /><category term="JK Rowling" /><category term="Harry Potter" /><category term="Theme" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/jk-rowling.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Starks Will Always Lose Game Of Thrones</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/why-starks-will-always-lose-game-of-thrones" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Starks Will Always Lose Game Of Thrones" /><published>2018-06-13T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-06-13T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/06/why-starks-will-always-lose-game-of-thrones</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/why-starks-will-always-lose-game-of-thrones"></content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Rowling used Story Structure</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/jk-rowling-story-structure" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Rowling used Story Structure" /><published>2018-06-11T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-06-11T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/06/jk-rowling-story-structure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/jk-rowling-story-structure"></content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="On Writing" /><category term="Book Studies" /><category term="Movies" /><category term="JK Rowling" /><category term="Harry Potter" /><category term="Structure" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/jk-rowling.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to write like JK Rowling</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-to-write-like-jk-rowling" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to write like JK Rowling" /><published>2018-06-10T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-06-10T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-to-write-like-jk-rowling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-to-write-like-jk-rowling">&lt;p&gt;You just come up with an awesome universe and spend five years world-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jokes aside, if you want to know how JK Rowling wrote Harry Potter, here’s what you need to know&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/jk-rowling-story-structure&quot;&gt;how Rowling used story structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2018/07/jk-rowling-foreshadowing-mystery-pacing-and-suspense&quot;&gt;how Rowling used foreshadowing, mystery, pacing and suspense&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/harry-potter-characters&quot;&gt;how Rowling created her Harry Potter characters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2018/07/jk-rowling-series-order-phoenix&quot;&gt;how Rowling uses series as threads for Order of The Phoenix plot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/the-theme-of-harry-potter&quot;&gt;what the theme of Harry Potter is all about&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out these articles and you’ll be on your way to understand all the tactics JK Rowling used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that being said, happy reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and don’t forget to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fiction.coach/free-courses/fantastic-five/&quot;&gt;Fantastic Five free email course&lt;/a&gt;. That will give you a very good head start in learning all of the above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you want to get serious about it, sign up for the waiting list of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fiction.coach/masterclass&quot;&gt;Fiction Coach Masterclass&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S: Remember what Rowling said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;fr&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Je. Meurs. O.M.G genre une auteure dont je suis fan depuis petite me répond et m&amp;#39;encourage. Genre je. J&amp;#39;ai pas les mots. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/p6ywqDqB9e&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/p6ywqDqB9e&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Roi-Sorcier d&amp;#39;Angmar (@_Uruk_Hai_) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/_Uruk_Hai_/status/929721771279953920?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;November 12, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="On Writing" /><category term="JK Rowling" /><category term="Harry Potter" /><summary type="html">You just come up with an awesome universe and spend five years world-building. Easy!Jokes aside, if you still want to know how JK Rowling wrote Harry Potter, you need to know:&amp;bull; how Rowling used story structure;&amp;bull; how Rowling used mystery, pacing and suspense;&amp;bull; how to create characters like JK Rowling.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/jk-rowling.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How To Write Bestsellers: Foreshadowing</title><link href="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-to-use-foreshadowing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How To Write Bestsellers: Foreshadowing" /><published>2018-06-07T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-06-07T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-to-use-foreshadowing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fiction.coach/2018/06/how-to-use-foreshadowing">&lt;p&gt;Foreshadowing is a vital tactic that’s simpler than it sounds and yet challenging to master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this sounds confusing, it’s because it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey, welcome to writing fiction! Now, don’t panic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that once you learn foreshadowing, your stories stand out and skyrocket to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heres-what-well-learn-in-this-article&quot;&gt;Here’s what we’ll learn in this article&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#definition&quot;&gt;What’s foreshadowing?&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#examples&quot;&gt;Examples of foreshadowing&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#got-foreshadowing-example&quot;&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#harry-potter-foreshadowing-example&quot;&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on-anything&quot;&gt;You can foreshadow pretty much anything you want&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#using-clues&quot;&gt;So foreshadowing means putting clues in your story, then?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#and-where&quot;&gt;Ok. Got it. Where do I use foreshadowing?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-three-sins-of-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;The three sins of foreshadowing&lt;/a&gt;:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dont-overdo-it&quot;&gt;Don’t use excessive foreshadowing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dont-foreshadow-crap&quot;&gt;Don’t foreshadow stuff that’s not interesting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dont-sponfeed&quot;&gt;Don’t spoonfeed with foreshadowing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;definition&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;What’s foreshadowing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreshadowing is paving the way to shock, revelation or relief in your story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It makes the plot twists believable and the story captivating, by giving readers hints.&lt;/strong&gt; It makes it easier for readers to buy your story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But. &lt;strong&gt;Foreshadowing isn't just dropping clues in your early stages.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know when you visit someone and there’s some cooking going on, but you can’t quite put your finger on what’s cooking, based on the smell alone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smell’s rather familiar, but you somehow know and hope that maybe it’s not exactly what you’re expecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’re expecting something thrilling or shocking would happen, that will jolt you from your day to day life.&lt;/strong&gt; Ok, this is going a bit far with just a dish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you know what I mean. &lt;strong&gt;At a basic level, we want to be surprised.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same thing with foreshadowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples-of-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;Examples of foreshadowing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be spoilers ahead, from Game of Thrones and Harry Potter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;got-foreshadowing-example&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-a-game-of-thrones-foreshadowing-looks-like&quot;&gt;How a Game of Thrones foreshadowing looks like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ned Stark’s execution by beheading was foreshadowed in numerous occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the three-fold revelation strategy that Martin uses to foreshadow events in Game of Thrones&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Ned Stark’s death was foreshadowed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the symbolism of the dead stag and the direwolf, from the beginning of the series, when Eddard and his entourage return from beheading the Night’s Watch deserter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the Lannisters, killing Lady, Sansa’s direwolf.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the secret conversation between Varys and Illyrio, the one that Arya witnesses in the dungeons – this, by the way, made me realize &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/why-starks-will-always-lose-game-of-thrones&quot;&gt;why Starks will always lose the game of thrones&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ned Stark’s death wasn’t foreshadowed just in those three places, but I think those were the most obvious stages and the most relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foreshadowing where Arya tells her dather that someone was talking about killing him and the way he reacts and dismisses Arya with her findings, also made me dislike the Starks – all, except Arya – given how, well, weak they are in playing the game of thrones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it just might be a slip in George Martin’s writing, trying to spoonfeed us on how gullible the Starks are. But more about this foreshadowing sin later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone told you “hey, I heard some dudes just round the corner, talking about stealing your car,” what would you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the Starks unskilled players in the game of thrones is an even greater foreshadowing that’s setting up the &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/why-starks-will-always-lose-game-of-thrones&quot;&gt;Starks as the main losers of the series&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tyrion is fascinated by how gullible and ill-fit the Starks are for the game, the whole time he’s taken captive by Catelyn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Freys playing the “mayhaps” game, where the King must hold to an oath, &lt;strong&gt;unless he slips in the word “mayhaps” unnoticed&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the discussion between Frey and Robb Stark, before the Red Wedding takes place. Frey slips in a “mayhaps” when the Starks ask for food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a shocker that he doesn’t keep his promise. He even mocks Robb about it. “You wanted to cross the river and get an army in exchange for my daughter’s hand, &lt;strong&gt;but you didn’t say mayhaps.&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;harry-potter-foreshadowing-example&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-a-harry-potter-foreshadowing-looks-like&quot;&gt;How a Harry Potter foreshadowing looks like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lore is so chock full of foreshadowing that we’re getting kind of spoiled here. But we’ll go for the most obvious one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snape as a double agent&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a mystery anymore that the great unsung hero of the Harry Potter books and movies is Severus Snape, the greasy haired double agent, who ultimately saved Harry Potter’s life countless times, by foiling Voldemort’s plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a scene, in the first book, that many people miss, but it’s there if you look hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Harry, who was starting to feel warm and sleepy, looked up at the High Table again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hagrid was drinking deeply from his goblet. Professor McGonagall was talking to Professor Dumbledore.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professor Quirrell, in his absurd turban, was talking to a teacher with greasy black hair, a hooked nose, and sallow skin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It happened very suddenly. The hook-nosed teacher looked &lt;strong&gt;past Quirrell's turban&lt;/strong&gt; straight into Harry's eyes — and a sharp, hot pain shot across the scar on Harry's forehead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-athr&quot;&gt;Harry Potter and The Philosopher's Stone - JK Rowling&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve bolded those words for you, so you can see JK Rowling’s trick at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JK Rowling sets up the double standard for Snape, by confusing us to his true intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“past Quirrell’s turban”&lt;/strong&gt; tells us that Voldemort is there, in one way or another. And he is, but not through Snape, as we expect it at first. It’s in Quirrel’s turban.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the series, we find out that Snape was actually working for Dumbledore, in revenge for Voldemort killing Lily Potter, the woman Snape loved and the woman Harry reminded him of, by looking into his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JK Rowling shows us how, &lt;strong&gt;almost always, the first thing people usually look for when they meet Harry Potter is his scar.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snape’s not doing that, though. He’s looking straight into Harry’s eyes. Lily’s eyes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you go back and re-read the books, Snape gives himself away as a good guy by not focusing on the scar, but on his love for Lily.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember this hint:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If your foreshadowing is obvious,&lt;/strong&gt; make sure you attach lots of emotion and meaning to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because, otherwise, it's the same with that cooking analogy: &lt;strong&gt;it either smells delicious or it makes you throw up.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;on-anything&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-can-foreshadow-anything&quot;&gt;You can foreshadow anything&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreshadowing is giving hints, implying and poking at your imagination.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s basically promising something that will or won’t be delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreshadowing means that you’re building tension but without being overt. It’s shipped in the form of some meaningless clue or some minor dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/how-to-write-like-jk-rowling&quot;&gt;how JK Rowling uses foreshadowing&lt;/a&gt; in her Harry Potter books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make this experiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While you're reading a book or watching a series and you come across something that doesn't need too much attention but it's there and the author points you in that direction, you might be experiencing foreshadowing then and there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;using-clues&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-foreshadowing-means-putting-clues-in-your-story-then&quot;&gt;So foreshadowing means putting clues in your story, then?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be. But it’s not a must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It depends on what you may call a clue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In book Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix, the fifth installment in the series, we have this passage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The others' hushed voices were giving Harry an odd feeling of foreboding; it was as though they had just entered the house of a dying man&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-athr&quot;&gt;When Harry first enters Grimmauld Place&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a dead-giveaway, once you re-read the books, that points directly at Sirius Black, Harry’s godfather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of foreshadowing like you’d think about &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/how-to-write-a-good-story#character&quot;&gt;character development&lt;/a&gt;: from the moment you learn how it works, it’s there for you to see it and take action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, &lt;strong&gt;foreshadowing is very useful when it comes to building a character and painting it inside your readers’ minds.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreshadowing is used to make the characters believable and fleshed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find out more about foreshadowing and character development in the upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://fiction.coach/masterclass/&quot;&gt;Fiction Coach Masterclass&lt;/a&gt; or you can check out the post about &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/how-arya-kills-the-mountain-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;how Arya kills The Mountain has been foreshadowed&lt;/a&gt;, based on the heavy foreshadowing that George Martin has used when building her character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;and-where&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ok-got-it-where-do-i-use-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;Ok. Got it. Where do I use foreshadowing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could argue that everything in the first part of your story – the first 25% – can be used as foreshadowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can foreshadow all the way up to the &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/how-to-write-a-good-story#structure&quot;&gt;Resurrection Plot Point&lt;/a&gt; – approximately 75% in the story. After this checkpoint, all foreshadowing will be useless, unless you’re writing a series like Harry Potter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, foreshadowing is tightly coupled with story structure. You can clearly see &lt;u&gt;how foreshadowing plays out throughout the Harry Potter saga&lt;/u&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about how foreshadowing and story structure work together, check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fiction.coach/free-courses/fantastic-five/&quot;&gt;Fantastic Five email course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the best way to study foreshadowing is to keep an eye out for it in the stories you love to read or watch, be them books, series, movies or games. Keep a count of those moments and see how they add up to the plot. There’s a difference between foreshadowing and character building, but they both provide a handshake that build a solid story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you learn the patterns, you’ll have a solid knowledge and be able to shock your fans with your foreshadowing strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreshadowing is one of the coolest ways to reward the people who read your books more than just once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;the-three-sins-of-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-three-sins-of-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;The three sins of foreshadowing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with everything good, foreshadowing can become one of those tools that can ruin your story, if&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you overuse it,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you use it to highlight unimportant stuff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or if you begin to spoonfeed your readers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s see how you can avoid that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;dont-overdo-it&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-use-excessive-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;Don’t use excessive foreshadowing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now know that foreshadowing can be a great tool to draw readers into your story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one surefire way to drive them away is to foreshadow virtually everything. This is how you’ll end up killing your story and fail to communicate anything of value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about what you love in your favorite stories. You love a story that’s tight and that moves from point A to point B, with a good amount of foreshadowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think you like stories where the author repeats themselves with things like “no one knew that this would happen” or “what were the odds of this going on?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t overuse foreshadowing for foreshadowing’s sake, otherwise, you’ll just kill the mood and you’ll make that grievous mistake that oh so many authors make: they tell instead of showing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing this, your readers will get confused with so many possible events coming their way, yet never satisfying their curiosity. And when that happens, you’re in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t foreshadow excessively. Otherwise you’ll lead people on stuff that’s not interesting and you’ll kill your story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;dont-foreshadow-crap&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-foreshadow-stuff-thats-not-interesting&quot;&gt;Don’t foreshadow stuff that’s not interesting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to let down your readers is to hint at something that’s about to come up later in the story and when it does &lt;strong&gt;it’s not something that impacts your plot or main characters.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, your readers would most likely feel that you’ve taken them for granted and wasted their time, by emotionally investing in something that wasn’t there from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me take a second here and add something that most authors seem to take for granted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;you have a relationship based on trust with your readers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you fail to deliver multiple times on that trust, your readers will abandon you and your stories. Aside from giving you their money for being entertained, they give you something much more valuable: &lt;strong&gt;their time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cherish this trust and reward your readers by using foreshadowing responsibly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;dont-sponfeed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-spoonfeed-with-foreshadowing&quot;&gt;Don’t spoonfeed with foreshadowing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter the genre of your fiction, your writing should be suspenseful. Take a page from JK Rowling’s book and learn &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/how-to-write-like-jk-rowling&quot;&gt;how JK Rowling made Harry Potter a Mystery&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core of every story, there must be something that delights through mystery and suspense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about that floating tension that’s keeping your nerves stretched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re telling instead of showing and you’re trying to help the readers to put the pieces together, &lt;strong&gt;you’re doing it wrong.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop spoonfeeding.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one will thank you for it and you’ll end up shooting yourself in the foot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreshadowing is useful, as you’ve probably come to guess by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your drooling sidekick, geeking out whenever you’re around. When you use it right and remember these three pitfalls we’ve just talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise it’ll just bite you in the ass and drive readers away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and before we end this, always remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;nk-blockquote&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;nk-blockquote-icon&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreshadowing is one of the coolest ways to reward the people who read your books, more than just once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/freefolk/comments/8pp898/george_rr_martins_editor_on_georges_threestep/&quot;&gt;George Martin three-step foreshadowing pattern&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/harrypotter/comments/1fymac/jk_rowling_perfects_the_art_of_foreshadowing/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How J.K. Rowling perfects the Art of Foreshadowing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fiction.coach/free-courses/fantastic-five/&quot;&gt;Fantastic Five email Course&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Crimson</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="On Writing" /><category term="Foreshadowing" /><summary type="html">It's simpler than it sounds and yet so challenging to master.Hey, welcome to writing fiction!Now, don't panic. You'll stand out and you'll see how your story skyrockets to the next level.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fiction.coach/assets/images/posts/resized/desk/foreshadowing-darth-vader.jpg" /></entry></feed>